{
  "reference_number": "11685",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "Reforestation, horticultural planting and improved soil health (which will absorb some of New Zealand’s carbon dioxide emissions),\n can be part of meeting our domestic net zero emissions target. Main focus must be rapidly reducing NZ’s greenhouse gas emissions\n - all gases, all sectors. NZ (businesses, iwi, communities, whānau, households, and all sectors including the health sector) needs\n\n certainty to act decisively now."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Unless it they get zero carbon earlier than 2050 - the earlier the better"
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Three 5-year emissions budgets covering the next 15 years, with our “legislated net zero emissions by 2040 target”, gives the\n\n certainty needed for action and investment now."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "The last budget should be able to be reduced if needed to respond to emerging international evidence. The Zero Carbon Act should\n also permit any Government to act so NZ can emit less than budgeted"
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "For business certainty reasons this needs to be as firm as possible. The Zero Carbon Act must require the Government to respond\n\nby publishing plans to stay within budget as rapidly as feasible within a set time limit that is certainly less than 12 months."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Equity / fairness within Aotearoa/NZ Treaty of Waitangi obligations. Health equity is essential in planning and monitoring . The\nsubstantial co-benefits to health from well-designed reduction and mitigation must be considered. Sustainable economic\n\nopportunities and technology relevant to climate change, to grow a fairer, just, sustainable Aotearoa-NZ. The Government must work\nin Te Tiriti partnership, and with NZ’s most vulnerable communities (those already disadvantaged and those working in high-\n\nemissions industries), to create a hopeful, fairer future."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Commission must set NZ’s Emissions Budgets independently from whatever government is in power. The Commission can also\nadvise how NZ stays within these budgets, how NZ can best adapt to climate change, and monitor progress on NZ’s emissions\nreductions"
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "The Commission should advise the Government on ETS policy settings so that New Zealand emits within budget"
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "On top of those listed, there are a number of essential areas that must be added - health expertise amongst Commissioners and\n\nstaffing is needed too. - expertise in achieving social change is also important. It is also essential that the Commission is founded on\npartnership with tāngata whenua and upholds obligations under Te Tiriti o Waitangi. It is important that vested interests, are not part\n\nof the Commission, particularly those with a financial interest in maintaining the health-harming status quo"
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Adaptation needs to be a separate work stream, to avoid distraction from the top priority of mitigation"
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I support the following adaptation provisions :   a national climate change risk assessment   a national climate adaptation plan  a\nregular review of progress towards implementing the national adaptation plan  an adaptation reporting plan  Mitigation and\n\nadaptation are often deeply interlinked - so often mitigation and adaptation can be addressed together in the same policy (e.g.\nhousing). But care must be taken in designing adaptation policies to ensure that climate-damaging emissions are not increased. A\nhealth adaptation plan must be put in place that covers both health sector adaptation and health-protecting adaptation in other\n\nsectors."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Farming emissions esp methane should be included as part of all greenhouse gases"
    }
  ]
}
